<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The middle-way in one paper of justification with indifferency between Protestant and papist / by J.H.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09657590</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09657590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1334:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The middle-way in one paper of justification with indifferency between Protestant and papist / by J.H.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justification.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43929:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Middle-Way In One Paper of JUSTIFICATION. With indifferency between <hi>PROTESTANT</hi> &amp; <hi>PAPIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By.</hi> J. H.</p>
            <q>Doing nothing by Partiality.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Three Bibles in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43929:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43929:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of</hi> Juſtification.</head>
            <p>IT is a trouble to to me often, in reading Polemical Divinity, to ſee how men that <hi>walk in a vain ſhew</hi> to others, and <hi>diſquiet themſelves in vain,</hi> are governed by <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Party:</hi> it is a hard thing many times, and a man muſt be very witty, and ſtrain himſelf to pick a fault in his Adverſary, <hi>for matter of contention;</hi> when a little pains only to underſtand him, and the leaſt candour, or, but a bare equality, in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, would bring him whether he would or no, almoſt, to <hi>reconciliation.</hi> The truth is, the Papiſts do abuſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and the Proteſtants abuſe the Papiſts, and that is the ſumme of moſt of our great Controverſies. I judge the like between Arminian and Calviniſts, and other Contenders. If <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> hath ſaid it, or <hi>Calvin</hi> hath ſaid it, it muſt be <hi>Heretical:</hi> and if the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> have delivered it, or <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaid ſo, it muſt be <hi>dangerous,</hi> it ſavours of the <hi>Harlot,</hi> it is the <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrine of the Church of Rome.</hi> Amongſt the many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts between this Church and us, there are few which are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on with that affection and concernment, as the diſpute of Juſtification. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was the firſt that engaged upon this point, and not without ſome warmth againſt thoſe that oppoſed him S. <hi>James</hi> is the next that hath ſpoken of this Subject. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church and the Fathers after them have accorded pretty well with both; but the School-men as I take it, by preſſing ſome paſſages of the Fathers over-cloſely, having obſcured the <hi>grace
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43929:3"/>of the Goſpel,</hi> our Proteſtant Churches have riſen up as it were under the <hi>ſtandard</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that is <hi>under his words,</hi> and the Roman Church under the words of St. <hi>James,</hi> and come out into a ſet Battel, which ſerving only to raiſe up <hi>duſt, darkneſs</hi> and <hi>doubt</hi> among the moſt, it is a <hi>conference</hi> I count be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Leaders,</hi> I mean a plain underſtanding or adjuſtment only of the <hi>one</hi> united certain ſenſe of <hi>both Apoſtles,</hi> inſpired by the ſame holy Spirit, that will, that muſt, and does give light to the intelligent and impartial, to uncloud the errors on each ſide, and end the quarrel.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>juſtify</hi> is from the word <hi>juſt,</hi> and one may be ſaid to be made or rendred juſt, by <hi>infuſion,</hi> or by <hi>plea.</hi> Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines do all teach us that the word is a forenſical term, and is to be underſtood in oppoſition to <hi>condemnation,</hi> for which they have good Scripture: the Papiſts doe tell us, that to juſtify a ſinner, is to make him righteous, and underſtand by it, in effect, the ſame thing with <hi>ſanctification.</hi> St.<hi>Auguſtine</hi> it muſt be acknowledged hath lead them this way. Gratificavit nos in dilecto, gratificavit a gratia, ſicut juſtificavit a juſtitia. <hi>De bono perſeverantiae,</hi> c. 6. Chriſtus juſtificat impium faciendo ex im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio Chriſtianum. <hi>Chriſt does juſtify the ungodly, by making him of one that is wicked, a holy man, or a Chriſtian,</hi> Contra litteras <hi>Petiliani</hi> l. 3. c. 45. There is his book <hi>De ſpiritu &amp; littera,</hi> where he hath the ſame up, and from whence a man may pick out his judgment on this point rather then any where leſe that I know. I did expect to find more, <hi>De fide &amp; operibus,</hi> but I perceive it does mainly reſpect another matter: we may ſee alſo his Book, <hi>De libero arbitrio &amp; gratia.</hi> The judgment then of this Father which leads the Schools in their diſputes about theſe matters, as to the main, comes to this. That God of his own goodneſs only, or free will, to wit, according to Election, does vouchſafe the holy Spirit to ſome Perſons, who does infuſe his grace in their hearts; which grace is that which diſposes them to all righteouſneſs, and is the ſame according to him, otherwhere with Charity, which fulfils the law, and ſo juſtifies us. And in this ſenſe does he tell us, that, Bona opera ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur juſtificatum, non praecedunt juſtificandum; that is, <hi>Good works do follow the Perſon juſtified, and do not go before juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43929:3"/>The meaning whereof with him is, that we muſt firſt have this grace infuſed (which habitually enclines to our whole duty both unto God and to our Neighbour), that is, the making the ungodly a juſt man, before he can do any thing that is good. <hi>Pelagius</hi> doctrine was, that grace is given according to our merits: but St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> doctrine is, that grace is firſt given, and good works follow.</p>
            <p>When the Apoſtle then does tell us that we are juſtified by <hi>grace,</hi> this Father I ſay underſtands by it this infuſed grace, that is, an habit of righteouſneſs infuſed into the heart, for fulfilling the law of God, and ſo juſtifies. Lex data eſt ut quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reretur gratia, gratia data eſt, ut lex impleretur. <hi>The law is given that grace may be ſought, and grace is given that the law may be fulfilled.</hi> De ſpir. &amp; lit. c. 19. In correſpondence to this, when the Apoſtle ſayes we are <hi>juſtified by faith,</hi> he tells us, that it is by its <hi>impetration of this grace.</hi> Impetrat orando, he has it in another place. Faith carries us to God, when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fulfill his commandements our ſelves, and by the infuſion of this habit he enables us to do it, and thereby are we juſtified in his Opinion. Quod operam lex minando imperat, hoc fidei lex credendo impetrat. Lege operum dicit Deus fac quod jubeo: lege fidei dicitur Deo da quod jubes. <hi>That which the law of works requires by threats, the law of faith obtains by believing. In the law of works, God ſaies, doe what I command: in the law of faith, we ſay to God, give what thou commandeſt.</hi> Ib. c. 12. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus quod qui fecerit vivet in eo, non fit niſi juſtificato: juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio autem ex fide impetratur. <hi>The works which he that does ſhall live in them, are not done but by the juſtified: and juſtification is impetrated by faith.</hi> c. 19. Lex non evacuatur ſed ſtatuitur per fidem, quia fides impetrat gratiam qua lex impleatur. <hi>The law is not made void, but eſtabliſhed by faith, becauſe faith fetches from God his grace whereby the law is fulfilled.</hi> c. 30. Now when he accounts that this grace which makes us juſt, or this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed grace is obtained by faith it is plain, that he muſt account that good works do follow it. Upon which there is a dfficulty might be propoſed to this Father, the ſpirit infuſes this grace: does faith then prhcede the ſpirit that infuſes it, or not? If it doe, then muſt our faith be of our ſelves, when our good works
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43929:4"/>are of his gift. And this indeed was his judgment, while he wrote this book, though after he recalled it in others. See par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>De gra. &amp; lib. arb. c.</hi> 5. Where he is proving that our converſion, and ſo faith it ſelf is from God.</p>
            <p>To go on, when the Apoſtle does oppoſe this <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> unto <hi>works,</hi> he is put to it: for, when by <hi>grace</hi> he underſtands nothing but infuſed righteouſneſs for the fulfilling the law, how does that oppoſe <hi>works?</hi> For the making his notion hold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by works in oppoſition to grace and faith he underſtands Opera ſine adjutorio &amp; dono Dei, <hi>works without the aſſiſtance and gift of God.</hi> In ſhort, our juſtification is not of works, which are done before we have grace: but of works which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from it. Iſrael non pervenit ad juſtitiam, quare? quia non ex fide ſed tanquam ex operibus: id eſt, tanquam eam per ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met ipſos operantes, non in ſe credentes operari Deum. <hi>Iſrael attained not to righteouſneſs, why? becauſe he ſought it not of faith, but as it were of works: that is, as working it out of themſelves, and not believing in God to work it in them.</hi> Ib. c. 19. So De gra. &amp; lib. arb. c. 8. Quomodo non ex operibus ne fortè quis extollatur! audi &amp; intellige, non ex operibus dictum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam tuis ex te ipſo tibi exiſtentibus, ſed tanquam his in quibus te Deus finxit. Ipſius enim figmentum ſumus creati in Chriſto Jeſu in operibus bonis. <hi>How, not of works that one may not boaſt? hear and underſtand, it is ſaid not of works as thy own done by thee of thy ſelf: but of thoſe as in which thou art created by God, for we are his workmanſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works.</hi> Again, Ignorantes Dei juſtitiam, id eſt, quae ex Deo eſt homini ut ſit juſtus: &amp; ſuam volentes conſtituere, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam per eorum non adjutam divinitus arbitrium lex poſſit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleri. <hi>Being ignorant of the righteouſneſs of God, that is, which comes from God to man, to make him righteous: and being willing to eſtabliſh their own, that is, as if by their own free-will without the divine help, they were able to perform the law.</hi> Contra duas E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolas Pelagianorum. l. 3 c. 1.</p>
            <p>In this doctrine of the Father, there are three things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is out.</p>
            <p>The firſt is in his conception of <hi>grace.</hi> When <hi>works</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> are oppoſed we are not to apprehend with him, that grace is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43929:4"/>taken for any thing infuſed in the Soul, which is inherent grace: for <hi>works</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> in this ſenſe have no oppoſition, the one being the fruits of the other. But by grace, we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the grace of God without us, the grace which is in God, that is, his favour or the condeſcention of God to us in this matter. And thus is the oppoſition very plain. That which is of <hi>debt</hi> is one thing, and that which is of <hi>favour</hi> another. <hi>Not of works,</hi> that is, not of debt, or of what would make the reward to be due: <hi>but of grace,</hi> that is, when it is not due, but of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. The certain truth is this, God Almighty gave to man a law according to his nature, which he repeated to the Jews, and if any man were able to keep this law according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Nature, then ſhould his juſtification be of <hi>right</hi> and <hi>due,</hi> according to the law of his creation: but the Apoſtle does moſt induſtriouſly prove, that neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile</hi> was able to produce theſe <hi>works,</hi> and conſequently if there be any, whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> that are juſtified, it muſt be by <hi>grace,</hi> becauſe it cannot be of <hi>right,</hi> or what he may challenge by the law upon that account. Grace then, and mark it well, is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of any mans perſon, or thing which is done, when one may chooſe, or when in juſtice one were not bound to do it. Accordingly, when God juſtifies us by grace, it is his accepting of us as righteous, or of what we doe, for righteouſneſs, and rewarding it as ſuch, when according to his law it would not <hi>ſtand,</hi> but he might condemn us for it. Let any who have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words uſe them, I regard only my ſenſe. And here may we have an anſwer to a queſtion of great heat amongſt our Divines. The Goſpel requires Faith, Repentance, and new Obedience, and how then are we juſtified and ſaved by <hi>grace,</hi> or how then is grace <hi>free,</hi> when it is not vouchſafed but upon <hi>conditions?</hi> This difficulty hath made ſome run into that extream, that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace is without condition: but I ſay readily, the grace of God, or of the Goſpel is <hi>free,</hi> in that he accepts of the ſinners faith and repentance, when he needs not, or when according to the <hi>law,</hi> he is not tyed to it, unleſs mans obedience were perfect. That which our Divines do offer uſually is this: It is free becauſe it is not of merit, mans belief and obedience cannot merit any thing at the hands of God, and much leſs ſalvation, as well from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43929:5"/>the diſproportion of our performances, or momentary ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, to the eternal weight of glory, with other the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as that we do herein but our duty, and he helps us alſo in the doing, which are the cheif reaſons that are urged. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation does labour I think with ſome defect of light. If man had performed the condition of the Covenant of works, it might upon theſe reaſons have been ſaid, that life and ſalvation, had been ſtill of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>free,</hi> as not merited, while theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations hinder merit: whereas the Apoſtle induſtriouſly oppoſing the ſinners being juſtified, or ſaved freely by Gods grace, to juſtification by works, or the deeds of the law, does account, if man were juſtifyed by <hi>works,</hi> it would be of <hi>debt.</hi> Could a man (I ſay) have performed the condition of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Nature, the Apoſtle accounts ſtill in his reckoning that then had the reward been of <hi>debt</hi> or <hi>merit,</hi> and if a mans own Conſcience could not accuſe him of ſin, he had no need of <hi>grace:</hi> but now ſayes he, ſeeing both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> fall ſhort hereof, and all are become guilty before God, there is none is, or can be juſtified, but it muſt be <hi>gratis, freely</hi> in oppoſition to that performance. To lend more help againſt this difficulty we muſt diſtinguiſh of merit. There is a debt or merit of <hi>commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> juſtice, or of governing <hi>diſtributive</hi> juſtice. It is impoſſible that any ſhould engage the Almighty in a debt of the former ſort. Of the latter fort, there is a debt or merit upon <hi>compact,</hi> or upon <hi>ſtrict retaliation.</hi> It is true, that there is nothing man does, or could do in the ſtate of innocency, had he continued perfect, can merit, or could have merited any reward from God, upon the ſcore of a ſtrict retaliation, or returning good for good, any more then upon commutative juſtice, becauſe there is nothing we can do to our Governour, who is infinite, to <hi>benefit,</hi> or <hi>hurt</hi> him: and ſo theſe reaſons before named of our Divines and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, may come in if they pleaſe. <hi>Can a man bee profitable to God,</hi> ſayes <hi>Eliphas</hi> to <hi>Job.</hi> And, <hi>who hath given to the Lord that he ſhould receive of him</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle. But the caſe is not ſo (under their favour) with a debt, or merit upon <hi>equal:</hi> and upon terms <hi>unequal.</hi> In a compact upon terms that are equal we are to know that the reward does become debt, or may be ſaid to be of merit, notwithſtanding by way of ſtrict retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43929:5"/>or upon an account of equal benefit, the performance of the condition would require no ſuch matter. For inſtance, if I agree to give a man half a crown for his dayes work, I muſt pay it him as <hi>debt,</hi> though the emolument to me by the work done, is not worth, it, nay, though if I had not agreed, I ſhould have thought much to give him half the money: but in a compact upon terms <hi>unequal,</hi> as if I promiſe a poor man a ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for his leading my horſe to the next ſtile, though I am bound to give it to him when he has done ſo, yet is the ſhilling an <hi>Almes,</hi> or the reward of <hi>grace,</hi> (or favour) for all that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now I account when God in the Covenant of Nature, hath made eternal life to be due upon exact obedience, it is a compact up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on terms but <hi>equal,</hi> he that <hi>doth them, ſhall live in them.</hi> So long as man was innocent, God in juſtice could not puniſh him: and ſo long as he continued but in the ſame ſtate he was created, he muſt be happy, and eternally ſo, which is the ſame thing with <hi>ſalvation,</hi> only it could not be called by that name, till man was firſt <hi>loſt.</hi> Neither may Gods giving him ability, or his doing no more then his duty, be any hindrance to him of meriting upon this compact, any more then my letting the man I have hired, to work with my ſhovel or mattock, and his doing only what he was bid, hinder him of his wages: the reaſon is, becauſe the compact ſuppoſes that if he does but his duty, with the ſtrength that God has given, or does give him, he ſhall be juſtified and bleſſed. If <hi>Adam</hi> then had, or we could perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Nature,</hi> which is to live perfectly without offending God at all, the reward no doubt (ſeeing the Apoſtle ſo accounts of it) ſhould be of <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>debt,</hi> for that was a Covenant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on terms but <hi>equal,</hi> it being <hi>meet</hi> that God ſhould deal benignly with us as his <hi>Creatures,</hi> while we carry our ſelves towards him as our <hi>Marker,</hi> and that he ſhould not deprive us of any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, to which we were <hi>created,</hi> before we forfeited it by our tranſgreſſion. But now when he gives us the reward, which is <hi>eternal life through his Son,</hi> upon an obedience which is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (that is by a new Covenant upon terms <hi>unequal</hi>) he gives it <hi>freely,</hi> ſeeing he gives it without performance of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition at firſt required to obtain the ſame. The ſum of this is, <hi>the rectoral</hi> juſtice of God is either under the <hi>ſtrict</hi> law, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43929:6"/>the <hi>law of grace.</hi> When our Divines then ſay that our works do not merit, they ſay true, but they muſt be rightly underſtood: when they give us thoſe reaſons for it, at firſt named, their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are good againſt all merit of <hi>commutative</hi> juſtice, and of ſtrict retaliation in <hi>diſtributive</hi> juſtice, and againſt merit <hi>ex pacto</hi> under the <hi>ſtrict law,</hi> or upon terms that are equal: but as to a merit of compact under the law of grace, <hi>ſecundum regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men gratiae pate num,</hi> they are not good. When by ſome of theſe reaſons therefore, our works, if they were perfect, ſhould not yet be meritorious, which is a contradiction to the Apoſtle, I muſt conclude that the reaſon why grace is ſaid to be <hi>free</hi> by St <hi>Paul,</hi> is not becauſe our works do not merit upon their reaſons, or do not merit with a merit of ſtrict retaliation, or, <hi>ex pacto,</hi> upon terms that are equal, which their reaſons only exclude: but becauſe we do not come up to thoſe (thoſe works), which notwithſtanding their reaſons, would merit if we did perform them; that is, becauſe they come ſhort of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which by Gods firſt compact according to <hi>nature,</hi> ſhould make the reward to be of debt, and yet God accepts of them for Chriſts ſake, and rewards them no leſs then if they did. That the grace of juſtification is purchaſed by Chriſt, it is apparent in the words that are ordinarily joynd with it, <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> But if the notion of <hi>free</hi> did lye in the conception, our DivInes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily frame, then could it not be the fruit of Chriſts pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, for how can that which is <hi>purchaſed,</hi> in their ſenſe be <hi>free?</hi> whereas it is this grace certainly, is the main fruit of Chriſts redemption, to wit, that the new Covenant ſhould be eſtabliſhed, ſo as the poor ſinner whoſe Conſcience does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him of the breach of that law, which is <hi>written in his heart,</hi> and according to which he ſhould dye, hath yet a refuge to Gods mercy, which he is ſaid, (I pray pardon me the repetition) to beſtow <hi>freely,</hi> becauſe man hath not the works which ſhould make the reward due to him. Lo then how the grace of God is ſaid <hi>free</hi> indeed in the meaning of the Apoſtle. Not upon the account, I ſay that man <hi>cannot merit at Gods hand,</hi> (though it be true that <hi>our works do not merit</hi>) as our Divines ordinarily only inform us, ſeeing both that God can be made
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43929:6"/>debtor <hi>ex pacto, regimine gratiae paterno,</hi> and Chriſt who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man did merit for us: but upon the account here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; which is a moſt direct anſwer to the doubt propoſed, how the grace of God can be free, which is not tendred and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained but upon condition; and I declare that Gods abatement of the terms, and requiring a <hi>new</hi> condition is that which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes it free, ſeeing it is tendred and obtained without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the <hi>old.</hi> As alſo that the new being <hi>unequal,</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not <hi>grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing wherein St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is out, is in his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Works.</hi> It is manifeſt that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of words in ſuch a ſenſe, as no man living can perform them, and upon that account no man can be juſtified by them. But if the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this Father, and the Papiſts after him were true, that by works we muſt underſtand works only that are done before a man is regenerate, or before he hath the help of the ſpirit, then may a man who is regenerate, and hath its help, perform the works that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, and ſo be juſtified by them. And then muſt his doctrine be falſe that comes to this univerſal concluſion. <hi>Wherefore we conclude that by the works of the law ſhall no fleſh living be juſtified in his ſight, for by the law is the knowledg of ſin.</hi> On the other ſide, when ſome Proteſtants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of our works in general, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that we are not juſtified by <hi>them,</hi> becauſe it is by the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> that we are juſtified, I cannot but think they are out likewiſe. For if when <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes we are not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by <hi>works,</hi> his meaning were, not by our <hi>own works,</hi> but by the <hi>obedience of Chriſt</hi> wrought for us: then when <hi>James</hi> ſayes we are juſtified by <hi>works,</hi> his meaning muſt be by the <hi>works Chriſt did for us,</hi> and he muſt not mean our <hi>own.</hi> But this is abſonant to any rational apprehenſion to conſtrue St. <hi>James</hi> ſo. Nor do I think ſuch a meaning ever came into the heads of either of the Apoſtles. Our Divines then ſhould not ſay here of our works in general, but as to the ſenſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of them in general, we are not juſtified them. And what is that ſenſe then in which he ſpeak of <hi>works?</hi> why he ſpeaks of works in that ſenſe moſt manifeſtly as the <hi>law</hi> require them, <hi>that we may live in them.</hi> Let a man then have the help of the ſpirit, or be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43929:7"/>without it, ſo long as he falls ſhort of what the law requires at his hands, be it never ſo little, he cannot <hi>live</hi> by thoſe works; the curſe is due to him for the leaſt breach, and that is contrary to juſtification. There are ſome Divines of note therefore, ſeeing no footing for this diſtinction, have choſe an other. There are works of the <hi>Law</hi> (ſay they:) and works of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes we are not juſtified by <hi>works,</hi> he ſpeaks expreſly of <hi>works of the Law:</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the <hi>works of the Goſpel.</hi> This diſtinction may ſerve well, provided it be cloathed with the ſenſe of the Apoſtles. When ſome have uſed theſe terms to ſignify no more but that we are not juſtifyed by Jewiſh obſervations, but by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Goſpel, it falls too ſhort in the firſt branch to do any thing. But by the <hi>works of the law</hi> let them underſtand <hi>works which anſwer the law,</hi> and that there are none juſtified by the <hi>works of the law,</hi> becauſe there is none perfectly fulfil it, and they have hit the buſineſs. For though <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks not only of works by the law of innocency, but directly and moſtly of the works of the Jewiſh law, which the Jews fancied, <hi>ex ſufficientia &amp; praeſtantialegis,</hi> did as ſuch, procure pardon and life, without looking to the merits of the Mediator for it, and ſo erred: yet the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> conſiſting either in <hi>moral</hi> precepts that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the law of Nature which no man can come up to, and the moſt righteous of them did break: or in the <hi>remedying</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of ſacrifices or attonements for ſin, whoſe virtue alone did lye in the blood of the Redeemer: the ground and bottom of their errour which he confuteth does indeed lye herein, that whatſoever it was they did, or whatſoever they thought of it, it did fall ſhort of the law of works, therefore did not juſtify them before God. There are works then which if they be performed doe <hi>anſwer the law,</hi> the law we are to mean ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately as given to mankind in a Covenant by our creation: and works which if performed do <hi>not anſwer the law,</hi> but anſwer the Goſpel. If the diſtinction before-cited be received with this meaning, it is true that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the works of the <hi>law,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> of the works of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and that there is no man juſtified by the <hi>former,</hi> becauſe there is no man does or can perform them, when we do perform the <hi>latter</hi> and are juſtified
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43929:7"/>by them. To give more light and weight to this. There are works which if we be juſtified by them exclude grace: and there are works which exclude not grace though we be juſtified by them. The works of the law, take them in this ſenſe, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the law if they be performed, muſt make juſtification due ſo as it may be challenged according to the law; the reward ſhall be of debt, and there be no need of grace but juſtice in the caſe, for he that doth them ought of right to live in them. And theſe are the works undoubtedly that <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes againſt, while he proves juſtification to be of grace; which is alſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the end and ſcope the holy Ghoſt ſeems to have in it, to wit, he beating man down from all vain exaltation in himſelf, and laying him at Gods feet for all he has. Wherein it were not yet enough that what he hath is received, ſeeing he would be even ready to boaſt of this, that he hath received what others have not: but that when he is enabled by God to perform that which he does, even this which he hath received, and is accepted, is but ſuch as God Almighty might chooſe whether he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it or not, and if it were not for <hi>grace,</hi> for all he hath done, he could not yet be juſtified and ſaved. On the contrary hand therefore, the works of the Goſpel, that is the works which the Goſpel requires of us as the condition of our juſtification and ſalvation, ſuch as faith, repentance, and new obedience, when they are performed, and anſwer the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> they do yet ſtand in need of grace, becauſe they do not anſwer the <hi>law,</hi> and God might chuſe whether he would accept them or no, or make any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to them. When we repent it includes the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, and when we believe, it is a flying to Gods mercy for it, and though we may walk <hi>ſincerely</hi> before God, we do not, and cannot walk <hi>perfectly,</hi> and he might condemn us is juſtice for the leaſt failings, and much more for our manifold tranſgreſſions. If God then ſhews mercy, and accepts of what we do, it muſt be of his grace that he does it. It is true that theſe works do juſtifie us, but that is while we are judged at the bar of Gods grace, or according to the new Covenant, which is therefore called a Covenant of grace, or the law of grace, becauſe that grace is no ways deſtroyed, but confirmed by theſe works. From whence it may appear that the two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43929:8"/>ſhall be ſo far from contradicting one another about this point, as that what St. <hi>Paul</hi> contends for, ſhall be made good by that which is ſaid by St. <hi>James. Paul</hi> ſayes we are juſtified by grace, and St. <hi>James</hi> proves it, while he ſhews us that our works which are <hi>imperfect</hi> (even ſuch as <hi>Rahabs</hi> as well as <hi>Abrahams</hi>) are accepted and rewarded as if they were <hi>perfect,</hi> that is, are imputed to us for righteouſneſs, which they could never be but for <hi>grace,</hi> and that purchaſed through the redemption which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The third thing wherein St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> miſtakes, is that which ſtrewes the way to the Papiſts doctrine or juſtification by <hi>works:</hi> and therefore it will be neceſſary before I come to it, to advance here ſomthing out of this Father which offers us I think ſome light towards the fixing our own doctrine of juſtification by <hi>faith. Per legem cognitio peccati: per fidem impetratio gratiae contra peccatum: per gratiam ſanatio animi a vitio peccati: per animi ſanitatem libertas arbitrii: per liberum arbitrium juſtuia dilectio: per juſtitiae d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lectionem legis impletio.</hi> De ſpir. &amp; lit. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>By the law we have the knowledg of ſin: by faith we impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate Gods grace againſt ſin: by grace the ſoul is healed from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: by that healing we have liberty of will: by this liberty we come to love righteouſneſs: by the love of righteouſneſs we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form or fulfil the law, and ſo are juſtified.</hi> Faith th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> does juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie according to him, as <hi>exordium hujus ad ſalutem connexionis</hi> (ſo he expreſſes it c. 31.), <hi>as the beginning work that brings on the reſt which follow in this connexion,</hi> or as the foundation link in this chain of our ſalvation. That we may be ſure of his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment herein this muſt not go without ſome quotation, from one of his latter books alſo. <hi>Ex fide antem ideo dicit juſtificari hominem, non ex operibus, quia ipſa prima datur, ex qua impetren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur caetera, quae proprie opera nuncupantur, in quibus juſte vivitur. The Apoſtle ſaith a man is juſtified by faith and not by works, becauſe it is faith that is firſt given, from whence they follow, or by which the grace of God to lead a holy life is obtained. De praedeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione ſanctorum. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. And unto this will I add the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage yet of a greater Authour, the Son of <hi>Sirach, Faith is the beginning of cleaving to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be here therefore two queſtions, <hi>de fide. Qua
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43929:8"/>juſtificat,</hi> and <hi>quâ juſtificat.</hi> What faith it is that juſtifies us? and, how faith juſtifies us?</p>
            <p>For the former it is agreed eaſily. That faith which <hi>worketh by love,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, or that faith which is <hi>made perfect by works</hi> as St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks, and no other is that which juſtifies us. There are ſome Divines make faith a complex thing to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend repentance and obedience under it. Faith, ſay they, is the receiving Chriſt both as Saviour and Lord, or the receiving him upon the terms of the Goſpel: and it is no wonder if they ſay faith alone juſtifies us, when his faith alone is no leſs with them then the whole condition which the Goſpel requires of us to our juſtification. Others do diſtinguiſh <hi>faith, repentance,</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> and ſay, that it is not <hi>faith</hi> alone, but <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>new obedience</hi> alſo is required to juſtifie us. And both theſe ſorts of Divines ſay but the ſame thing in effect, and agree in their meaning. When the Scripture therefore ſayes, <hi>If thou believeſt thou ſhalt be ſaved, or if thou repenteſt thou ſhalt be ſaved, Bellarmine</hi> ſayes ſuch Texts muſt be underſtood with the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>ſi caetera adhibeantur,</hi> that is, <hi>if that which is required alſo elſe where is ſupplied.</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſaved if thou repenteſt, provided thou alſo believeſt: and if thou believeſt thou ſhalt be ſaved, provided alſo thou repenteſt and walkeſt ſincerely before God. I mean, provided thou reſolves upon a changed upright life, and if thou art not prevented, bringeſt this reſolution to practice, there being no doubt but if a man dye before oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, his conſent to the Covenant is to be reckoned for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and baptiſme alwayes waſhes away ſins with the Fathers. <hi>Non concluditur legitime</hi> (ſaies a judicious Proteſtant Divine) <hi>a poſitione unius diſperati ad negationem alterius: neque ab eo quod aliquot locis docetur, ad negationem corum quae alibi aſſeruntur.</hi> And this I take to be more after St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and St. <hi>James,</hi> who do both methinks make faith the <hi>initium &amp; fundamentum</hi> (to uſe his words) the <hi>foundation</hi> and <hi>entrance</hi> to obedience and good works, and ſo to juſtifie us as it is productive of them. We ſhall reconcile all I hope if we ſay only, that faith indeed may be <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> when not <hi>divided</hi> from our obedience in our juſtification. That is in ſhort, <hi>faith,</hi> is one thing, and <hi>juſtifying faith</hi> is another, and yet juſtifying faith retain the common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43929:9"/>ſtill of <hi>faith.</hi> Juſtifying faith, I take it, is ſuch a believing of, or truſting to Gods mercy, that he will pardon our ſins if we repent and walk ſincerely before him (which are the terms ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for us through Chriſts redemption), as produces that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and ſincere walking. It is ſuch an <hi>aſſent</hi> to what God reveals, as carryes the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life</hi> along with it. I believe his <hi>promiſes</hi> (to wit effectually) when I ſo truſt them, as to do the things he requires of me to obtain them. I believe his <hi>precepts</hi> when I keep them. I believe his <hi>threats,</hi> when I abſtain from the evil he forbids, to avoid them. I believe the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> when I become Chriſts Diſciple. <hi>Credere is fidelis eſſe</hi> according to <hi>Salvian,</hi> and to be faithful is to doe our duty. <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the latter, I do not apprehend ſeriouſly (if I may ſpeak freely my thoughts, to which very end do I write) but that there is a great deal more ſtir and difference among Divines in this point of <hi>juſtification by faith</hi> then needs in late times. If any man might meerly by his believing Chriſt dyed for him, and hath carryed away all ſin, be juſtified and ſaved, let him live as he liſt holding ſtill but this perſwaſion, there were ſomething in our contending for juſtification by faith alone, and a man would not be bereaved of the comfort of ſuch a doctrine for the World. But when we all agree that whether good works do juſtify or no, good works in the <hi>reſolution,</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> if not prevented, are neceſſary ſome way or other, ſo that no man living ever was or can be juſtified that is deſtitute of them, I doubt me verily our contention in this matter is rather <hi>curious</hi> then <hi>profitable,</hi> in ſhewing how faith <hi>without works,</hi> but not a faith, <hi>which is without works</hi> (at leaſt in the will and intention) does juſtify. I know our Divines againſt in the Papiſts contend that faith juſtifies <hi>in ſenſu correlativo,</hi> or in regard of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſo as to be juſtified by Chriſts blood, and by faith is all one, that is by faith in his blood. The righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed is the <hi>formal</hi> ſay ſome, or as others had rather ſay the <hi>material</hi> cauſe of our juſtification, and faith juſtifies as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. For my own part I will tell you therefore what I have ſometimes ſet down for truth in my <hi>contending belief,</hi> and what I think in my cold <hi>practical conceit</hi> of the point.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43929:9"/>
            <p>As for my former thoughts I have ſome times pitched them thus. Juſtifying faith is the <hi>receiving act</hi> of a <hi>working habit,</hi> as hath the other act too to out forth upon trial, or elſe it is but a <hi>dead</hi> faith. Now this faith I have counted juſtifies as an <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> not <hi>mans,</hi> who doeth not juſtify himſelf, but <hi>Gods</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment though mans act. This I have made out to my ſelf thus. Unto juſtification there goes two things, the <hi>imputation</hi> of Chriſts righteouſneſs for the diſcharge of ſin, and accepting us unto life: and a <hi>valid donation</hi> of it to the ſinner. The laſt is the ground of the former; for man muſt be <hi>made juſt,</hi> or God cannot reckon him ſo, and acquit him in judgement. <hi>The judgement of God is according to truth.</hi> Now to this making a man juſt, as there is this <hi>donation</hi> of God, there muſt be mans receiving, Chriſt is not ours though tendered or given until we receive him. This receiving then (which is our act, that is faith it ſelf) God excites, and make uſe of to this end. He makes uſe of it (I have accounted) as his inſtrument of making Chriſt ours, to this end he hath apppointed it for, that he may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly reckon his righteouſneſs to us, unto the remiſſion of ſin and everlaſting ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Having told you this firſt, I may make the bolder to tell you my more indifferent thoughts of farther years. I do appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that the Apoſtles in their doctrine, and the Primitive Chriſtians, had more ſimple and leſs intricate conceptions of things then we have; and that their diſpute then whether we are juſtifyed by faith or works, in the moſt ſimple underſtanding of it, contains no more than to ſhew us what is required of perſons that they may be juſtified, or what is that God hath made the condition on our parts of our juſtification. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> I have ſaid, does teach us that faith does juſtifie us as the beginning and foundation unto grace and a good life, and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and the Papiſts after that Council ſtand upon this. Faith juſtifies only as <hi>initium juſtificationis,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of juſtification. But howſoever the Papiſts have made uſe of that Father, the truth and light which he hath offered, is not to be loſt; I do take this to be the moſt right and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain notion that faith does juſtify as <hi>initium</hi> and <hi>fundamentum;</hi> I will not ſay <hi>juſtificationis,</hi> ſeeing I underſtand not juſtification to be all one with ſanctification as they do, but as <hi>fundamentum
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43929:10"/>conditionis.</hi> The condition of our full &amp; final juſtification the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel offers, is repentance and ſincere obedience, and faith is the <hi>initium</hi> and <hi>fundamentum</hi> of that condition. <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>our Father juſtified by works when he had offered his Son</hi> Iſaack, ſayes St. <hi>James?</hi> The faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> or his believing God, was the beginning and foundation of this excellent work, the ready offering his Son, which ſhewed his ſincerity of life, the condition of juſtification. <hi>And the Scripture was fulfilled which faith</hi> Abraham <hi>believed God, and it was imputed to him for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> Here <hi>believing</hi> &amp; <hi>offering Iſaac</hi> are all one with S. <hi>James.</hi> The Offering <hi>Iſaack</hi> proceeded from believing, as the <hi>initium</hi> and <hi>fundament u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of it, and ſo believing as the <hi>initium</hi> of ſincerity of life or ſincere obedience does juſtifie. Such a faith as produces good works which are ſincere though imperfect, or ſuch good works as proceed from faith, are but one and the ſame thing with the two Apoſtles, and made by both the condition of our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhould be willing to come off: but the uniform judgement of the reformed Churches on the Article of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion requires ſome regard. There is therefore in the Schools, a <hi>Quatenus ſpecificative, &amp; reduplicative.</hi> I ſuppoſe when I have ſaid that faith does juſtifie us as the foundation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition (and ſo productive of the whole of it) I have ſaid well with S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> as to the <hi>quatenus ſpecificative,</hi> and if I ſaid nothing elſe it might be enough. Nevertheleſs, ſeeing it is but fit upon this account to ſpeak yet a little more curiouſly, I muſt needs ſay farther, that I apprehend there is indeed ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in that which lyes in the concurring thoughts of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that faith hath, and muſt have a hand in our juſtification ſomeway, as no other of our works of acts have. It is this. I believe that God will pardon me if I repent, and therefore I repent, as my faith now makes me repent and perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, it juſtifies me, as to a <hi>quatenus ſpecificative:</hi> but when I have repented and performed the condition, the duties I have performed are imperfect and ſinful, and have need of mercy in point of law, and it is my faith yet muſt go to God for his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of them through Chriſt when I have done. It is my faith, let my ſay, that muſt make up to me, out of the mercy or grace of God for Chriſts ſake, what is wanting in that I have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43929:10"/>done, to make it ſuch as he may impute it to me for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which elſe he could not. And as faith procures me this, or procures it thus, we have the <hi>quatenus</hi> alſo <hi>reduplicative,</hi> in the great queſtion how faith juſtifies. It is faith makes me perform the condition, and then finds acceptance for it being done; and as it does both, it does <hi>ſpecificative,</hi> and <hi>reduplicative</hi> juſtifie the ſinner. By this, it appears how faith hath an eye ſtill to pardon according to the Proteſtant, while it is oppoſed to works in the point of juſtification, which is not only as reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pardon of all our ſins upon the performing the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but as reſpecting that pardon more eſpecially which goes into the very accepting the condition performed; for when there is imperfection ſtill in our duty, and yet he accepts it, he muſt pardon alſo, what he accepts. And thus it is that the <hi>juſt man</hi> is ſaid to <hi>live by faith</hi> in the moſt ſubtle conception. The works which the juſt man does are <hi>his righteouſneſs</hi> moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and that which juſtifies him; but they are ſhort, and he could not <hi>live</hi> in them, but that faith ſupplies (as I ſpeak) out of Gods pardon and grace, and conſequently out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Chriſts ſake, what is wanting otherwiſe for acceptation unto life. I do not ſay faith ſupplies this out of Chriſts merits, as if <hi>his</hi> and <hi>our</hi> obedience were mingled, to make up that <hi>one</hi> righteouſneſs that juſtifies us: but that it is our works which we perform our ſelves, is the condition, and through Chriſts merits, both the imperfection is pardoned, and they accepted, according to covenant, upon faith. <hi>It is of faith</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Paul, that it might be of grace.</hi> To be of <hi>works,</hi> is to need to grace: but to be of <hi>faith,</hi> is to have ſuch works as need to be pardoned, even when they are accepted of God, for Chriſts ſake, unto everlaſting ſalvation. When <hi>Auguſtine</hi> does tell us ſo often that faith juſtifies, <hi>gratiam impetrando,</hi> let us take <hi>grace</hi> in <hi>his,</hi> and alſo in <hi>our</hi> acception, and both together will compleat the notion. Faith goes to God for his grace, or <hi>help,</hi> whereby we perform the condition, and ſo juſtifies us: Faith goes to God alſo for his grace or <hi>favour,</hi> to pardon and accept what is done for Chriſts ſake, and ſo juſtifies us. As it does im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate grace, or obtain his ſpirit for our duty: and then impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates grace, or finds favour alſo for acceptance of it, taken them both together, and we underſtand fully how we are juſtified by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43929:11"/>Faith. As our truſting to a good man, does naturally draw out, win, or procure his aſſiſtance which yet is free and not of debt: ſo does our truſting in God for acceptance, when it hath firſt been effectual upon us to the performing our part to that end, procure the ſame from him to our juſtification. Let us take heed of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith a <hi>ſingle</hi> act as it does <hi>ſpecificative:</hi> and a <hi>complex</hi> act, as it does <hi>reduplicative</hi> juſtifie the believer. Theſe are two extreams I think, and to be thus compoſed. And ſo you have my poor thoughts at full upon this vexed queſtion.</p>
            <p>I come then to the third thing wherein the Father is out, and that is in his notion of juſtification it ſelf, which is the making us juſt, by infuſion. This the Papiſts have ſo improved, as in effect to exclude pardon from it. For while they place the work of juſtification in the aboliſhing of all ſin in the <hi>baptized</hi> and <hi>juſtified,</hi> ſo that there remains no longer any thing that is <hi>peccatum,</hi> but fomes <hi>peccati</hi> only, they do, I muſt ſay in effect, put us to diſpute with them, whether there by any remiſſion of ſins at all, ſeeing the wicked are not pardoned, and the juſtified have their ſins ſo done away by this infuſed grace, as to have none; and from hence does there ſpring their doctrine of <hi>merit,</hi> and <hi>perfection,</hi> which the controverſie of <hi>juſtification by works,</hi> does carry along with it. Now I doubt not but the truth here (as it doth every where), is ſuffering between two theives. That there is no <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>perfection</hi> I am convinced, and that our works do not <hi>merit</hi> becauſe they are not <hi>perfect;</hi> but that we are juſtified by <hi>works,</hi> as we are by <hi>faith,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> his words muſt goe as well as St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and both muſt ſtand good, becauſe faith juſtifies only as productive of works. Juſtification indeed is by <hi>works,</hi> but not <hi>meritorious works:</hi> by works which make reward to be of <hi>debt,</hi> ſo the Apoſtles are before reconciled. There are two queſtions then may adjuſt this great matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Us and the Papiſts, or unto which the iſſue of our diſputes on this point may be reduced. In the one they have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of us, in the other we have the better of them. The lover of truth muſt be humbly hardned to follow its footſteps whereſoever he finds them, whither on the one ſide or the other.</p>
            <p>The firſt queſtion is, whether the righteouſneſs we perform
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43929:11"/>our ſelves, or that Chriſt performed for us, be the <hi>matter</hi> of our juſtification? and I ſay, the faith, repentance, new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which the Chriſtian through divine aid performes himſelf, is accepted with God for Chriſts ſake unto pardon of ſin, and eternal life. It is true, the obedience of Chriſt wrought for us, does juſtifie us <hi>ſuo genere,</hi> by meriting the pardoning, juſtifying Covenant, which is the donative inſtrument of pardon and life: But if the queſtion be askt, whether we have performed that which this inſtrument requires as <hi>conditio tituli,</hi> it muſt be our own faith and repentance here that is the <hi>matter</hi> of our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. A man may be juſt in reſpect to the law of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which no man but Chriſt ever was: or in reſpect to the law of grace, which all are, and muſt be, that are ſaved. Again, a man may be juſt in reſpect to the <hi>perceptive</hi> part of a law: or the <hi>retributive</hi> part. It is Chriſts righteouſneſs and ſacrifice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that juſtifies Us in regard of the one, but not ſo in regard of the other: yet is it that alone which is the meritorious cauſe both of the acceptation of what we do, and freedom from the Laws condemnation. The ſecond queſtion is, whether ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation then and juſtification is not according to our <hi>merits?</hi> And I anſwer, as the Scripture is cleer and full from one end to the other for the <hi>affirmative</hi> in the <hi>former</hi> queſtion: ſo is the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as full and cleer and poſitive as can be for the <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> in the <hi>latter.</hi> What is it indeed he beats upon but this altogether? that there are no works in the earth (Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) that do merit: and that juſtification and ſalvation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are of grace. <hi>Not of works, but of grace.</hi> What is that in the ſenſe and meaning, but as much as if he ſhould have ſaid it in expreſs terms, not of <hi>merit,</hi> but of <hi>grace,</hi> or, not of works that are meritorious, and would make the reward to be of debt: but of ſuch works that though they be rewarded, it is of grace, and more then in juſtice according to the law, God needed to have done. For this is the meaning of the Apoſtle in excluding of merit. There is a paternal government according to the law of grace wherein the denyal of a reward due to our works were to overthrow all religion: A good child by his filial behaviour merits love and benefits: We diſpute not unleſs <hi>de nomine</hi> only, againſt ſuch a merit as this. But as to a merit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43929:12"/>in Gods <hi>ſtrict diſtributive</hi> juſtice according to the law of works or any <hi>other</hi> juſtice which ſhould make our works to be merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>ex condigno, non ſolum ratione pacti &amp; acceptationis, ſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione operis,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> with the Papiſts does ſpeak, St. <hi>Paul</hi> is full in the deny<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>l. It is nothing elſe certainly but the miſapprehenſion of the word <hi>grace</hi> in St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> received by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from him, that could have blinded them ſo in this point. I have ſhown his miſtake in this term, and in thoſe of <hi>works,</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> and have and do here give you the right ſenſe of each according to the Apoſtle. The certain truth is this, God gave a law to man according to his creation, and if he had performed that, or any of us could perform that, then ſhould he as Creator and Rector be engaged to reward the performance according to this law, ſo that the reward ſhould be of right: but ſeeing man is fallen, and no Perſon on earth does or can perform that law, there are no works on earth that do properly merit, or no man on earth that can be juſtified, if he have only his deſert by his works. This is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the very entendment of the Apoſtle. That all <hi>boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>merit</hi> may be excluded from the world, while it is proved that no mortal is juſtified or ſaved but by <hi>grace.</hi> And what need further conviction in this matter? we have the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts own words, and general confeſſions, that they are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and that it is through Chriſts merits that they merit. If they are ſinners then have they not theſe works that are merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, but it muſt be of mercy that they are not condemned; and if it be through Chriſts merits that they merit, then is the reward not for the <hi>work</hi> ſake, but for <hi>his.</hi> And what is it that Chriſt hath <hi>merited,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>merit?</hi> It muſt come to this, that Chriſt by what he hath done for us, hath merited or procured this grace or favour from God, that he ſhould accept of our imperfect performances, which could not elſe be accepted, to ſalvation. Of this grace he hath made and promulgated the <hi>promiſe.</hi> Upon the promiſe the reward becomes <hi>due.</hi> A reward upon promiſe the condition being performed, becomes debt. And thus if the Papiſts ſay their good works merit, the uſe of the word is common with the Antients. Well then, let me recount this back to them, their good works merit,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43929:12"/>that is only, they make the reward due from God. They make it due from him, that is only becauſe of his promiſe. <hi>Debet ſibi, non tibi,</hi> ſayes the Father. This promiſe is only of grace, or made freely out of favour procured by Chriſt. Our good works then muſt have ſuch a merit attributed to them, as makes the reward due only of <hi>grace</hi> and for <hi>Chriſts ſake:</hi> and not ſuch as makes it due of <hi>right</hi> or juſtice, and for the <hi>works ſake.</hi> And ſuch a merit; what is it indeed but no merit, or but a word on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? It is ſuch a merit as our perfect works which anſwer the law would have if we did them, to make the reward to be ſo of <hi>debt,</hi> as <hi>not</hi> to be of <hi>grace,</hi> that we diſpute againſt, and the Apoſtle, in this doctrine of juſtification.</p>
            <p>To return to <hi>Auguſtines</hi> errour. Juſtification I verily believe is to be taken in the Proteſtants notion, who do no leſs truly and judiciouſly, then induſtriouſly diſtinguiſh ſanctification and juſtification: and when they place the one in the work of the ſpirit renewing the whole man, and enabling us to dye unto ſin, and live unto God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do place the other in an act of Gods grace whereby he pardoneth all our ſins, and accepteth us as righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for Chriſts ſake. As for what they add uſually in the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition that Chriſts righteouſneſs is imputed to us, and made ours by faith as an inſtrument, I muſt confeſs they are notions, which as they never came into the head of St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> nor were received (I ſuppoſe) in the Church till within a century or two of years ſince: ſo do I queſtion whether a Century or two more may not wear them quite away again. That the righteouſneſs of Chriſt performed in the whole courſe of his life and death was ſo pleaſing, acceptable, and ſatisfactory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God, that the whole World upon that account, or for the merit of it, ſtands reconciled to him ſo far as that he hath vouchſafed a univerſal conditional pardon, or law of grace, to all mankind, according to the tenour of the Goſpel, and conſequently that every Perſon who truly repents and believes, are made partakers thereof in regard of this benefit, or in the effect, is a truth which we embrace: but when this very phraſe of the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts righteouſneſs is not found in the Scripture, and the terms are uſed conſtantly in ſuch a ſenſe as if we were to be taken for perfectly righteous in Chriſts obedience, and to have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43929:13"/>ſatisfied the law in his ſufferings all one as if our ſelves had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the ſame, that is, as if it were ours, <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> and not only in the <hi>benefit,</hi> or as to the end or intent Chriſt performes it for us, it is a conception of ſuch another extream to that of St. <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> as requires alſo our equal rectification.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt through the Scripture, that good works, holy duties and performances of men and women, are accepted of God, and ſo accepted, that they are rewarded by him with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation. <hi>If thou wilt have life, keep the commandements. To them who by patient continuance in well doing ſeek for glory, eternal life. I have fought the good fight, therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is laid up for me a Crown of righteouſneſs. Come ye bleſſed of my Father, for when I was a hungry ye fed me.</hi> If then the keeping the Commandements, a patient continuance in well doing, the fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good fight, and our works of charity be produced in judgment, as that for which we are declared righteous, abſolved and pronounced bleſſed, It muſt be in ſome ſounder then the ordinary ſenſe, that our Divines bring in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be imputed to us for our juſtification; which if it be more then abſolution from ſin, and acceptation of us to eternal life, let it be weighed and judged.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the Lord is ſpeaking of the righteous man, and repenting ſinner. <hi>When the righteous turneth from his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and committeth iniquity, ſhall he live? his righteouſneſs ſhall not be mentioned, but in his ſin which he hath ſinned, he ſhall dye.</hi> Again, <hi>If the Wicked turn from his ſinnes and does that which is right, all his tranſgreſſions which he hath committed ſhall not be mentioned; in his righteouſneſs that he hath done he ſhall live.</hi> It is apparent from hence, that there is a righteouſneſs which is a mans own, a righteouſneſs which he hath <hi>done,</hi> wherein the righteous man that continues in it, or the penitent ſinner that turns to it, ſhall <hi>live.</hi> To live in a mans righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs beyond doubt, is all one to be juſtified by it. <hi>He that doth them</hi> faith the law <hi>ſhall live in them,</hi> that is ſhall be juſtified by them. If you make a queſtion, there is another Text muſt convince you. <hi>The juſt man ſhall live by his faith.</hi> What is it to live by our faith? that you will not deny, is to be juſtified by it; for the Apoſtle alleadges this Scripture to prove juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43929:13"/>by Faith. Well! There is no man of reaſon now can imagine that the righteouſneſs which is here ſpoken of, is Chriſts righteouſneſs, and yet the righteouſneſs which is here, is that, a man ſhall live in. It follows, that it is not therefore the righteouſneſs of Chriſt from without imputed, but the righteouſneſs which man himſelf does (through Chriſt indeed and his ſpirit aſſiſting) whereby he muſt be juſtified and ſaved. It is by his <hi>faith</hi> that he ſhall live in one Prophet, and by his <hi>righteouſneſs which he hath done,</hi> in another. Put them together, and they come to one, as they muſt doe, and that is, by the righteouſneſs of faith; to wit, by that righteouſneſs of life, or holy working which faith produces in a godly mans converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which God requires every where as the condition of the forgiveneſs of his ſins, and the acceptation of him to life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved by <hi>Arminius</hi> that the Apoſtle does ſeveral times in one Chapter (I forget the number,) tell us that faith is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for righteouſneſs. That <hi>Abrahams was,</hi> that ours <hi>ſhall,</hi> or <hi>is,</hi> again and again. But it is no where ſaid that Chriſts righteouſneſs is imputed to us for righteouſneſs. Indeed the phraſe could not be ſo uſed. We might ſay properly enough (ſuppoſing it true in the common conſtruction) that Chriſts righteouſneſs were imputed: but not imputed for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For to be imputed for righteouſneſs is to ſtand one in ſtead of perfect righteouſneſs, which cannot be ſaid of Chriſts, ſeeing that it ſelf was moſt perfect. A thing cannot be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inſtead of that which it is. This Argument now of <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> is good. It is faith which is a mans own act that is imputed for righteouſneſs, therefore, not the righteouſneſs, acts, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of another. But when this acute Divine would intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a notion hereupon, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>credere,</hi> therefore muſt juſtifie us, and not <hi>works,</hi> or not the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>operari,</hi> it is both an ill and weak conceit, which is neither of uſe nor value. For as the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>faith</hi> being accounted for righteouſneſs, ſo does it tell us that <hi>Abrahams offering his Son,</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> act were accounted to them for righteouſneſs, and that <hi>Rahabs</hi> hiding the Spies did juſtifie her. That is, it is faith as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of works, or works as produced by faith that receives
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43929:14"/>the reward of perfect righteouſneſs, which is, we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo for Chriſts ſake, or through his merits; not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us as proprietors, but prevailing with the Father for ſuch terms for ſinners as anſwers our redemption and grace of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I would fain know of any man who is moſt Orthodox in his complexion, whether he does, or is able to think, that <hi>Enoch, Noah, Job,</hi> who were before the law, <hi>Samuel,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> who were under the law, or any man or woman whatſoever before the coming of Chriſt, did ever imagine that they were righteous, and to be accepted with God for the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould perform in their behalf when he came into the world, and that the believing this was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of making it to be theirs, and ſo to be imputed to them which it could not be elſe: or whether they did not look on themſelves to be righteous by doing righteouſly, and to obtain Gods favour by their upright walking with him, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the World? They judged not their own righteouſneſs the meritorious cauſe of pardon to anſwer the Curſe of the Law of Innocency, but they believed in Gods mercy, and ſo repented, obeyed, and were ſaved through the Redeemer. <hi>And</hi> Enoch <hi>walked with God, and God took him.</hi> Bleſſed is the man ſayes <hi>David</hi> who <hi>walkes in his wayes, and to whom he imputeth no ſin.</hi> In the acceptation then of a mans own upright walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in the pardon of his ſins, did our juſtification and bleſſedneſs lye in <hi>Davids</hi> time: and in the ſame no doubt does it lye ſtill under the Goſpel. I would yet fain know whether any of the Diſciples, <hi>James, John</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, whether <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Roman,</hi> or <hi>Alexandrine, Juſtin Martyr, Cyprian, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Auguſtine,</hi> or any of the Fathers, whether Councels, or School-men, whether <hi>John Hus,</hi> or <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> or any famous or holy Writer (without reſting on ſome bare incoherent ſcraps of ſentences) did ever underſtand, or receive the full no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faiths inſtrumentality, and the imputation of a paſſive righteouſneſs before <hi>Luther?</hi> And if not, whether it be poſſible it ſhould be of any ſuch moment as is made of it by moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants? It was an Article indeed that raigned in <hi>Martins</hi> heart, and I do therefore give it my obeyſance: but it is no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43929:14"/>Article I take it, as the remiſſion of ſins is, in the Creed of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>If the righteouſneſs of Chriſt be imputed to us (as if it were ours in it ſelf) it muſt be the righteouſneſs of his <hi>active,</hi> or <hi>paſſive</hi> obedience, or <hi>both.</hi> If his <hi>active</hi> obedience be imputed to us, then muſt we be lookt upon in him as ſuch who have committed no ſin, nor omitted any duty, and then what need will there be of Chriſts death! how ſhall Chriſt dye for our ſins if we be lookt on in Chriſt as having none at all? If Chriſts <hi>paſſive</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience be imputed, then muſt we be look't on as ſuch who in Chriſt have ſuffered and ſatisfied the law, and born the full curſe of it; and then how ſhall there be room for any pardon? The man who payes his full debt by himſelf or ſurety, can in no ſenſe be forgiven by his Creditour. Indeed the Argument of the <hi>Socinian</hi> from pardon againſt Chriſts ſatisfaction is not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid: but it is good againſt the imputation of it to us as if we our ſelves had ſatisfied. Chriſt may have wrought with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (or made him that ſatisfaction as) to procure new terms, ſo that a man may be juſtifyed as a fulfiller of them, and yet need pardon for non-performance of the old. If Chriſts active and paſſive obedience both are imputed, then muſt God be made to deal with man according to the <hi>Covenant of works</hi> in the buſineſs of his juſtification, when nothing is more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the Scripture than that by <hi>grace</hi> it is, that a man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by <hi>grace</hi> ſaved. If nothing leſs then ſuch a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as does both anſwer, and ſatisfie the law alſo, and that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, will ſuffice for the ſinners plea to free him from condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is not judged by the <hi>law of grace,</hi> but he is judged by the <hi>law of works,</hi> out of queſtion. There were no need to bring this notion of Chriſts imputed righteouſneſs into the Church, but that our Proteſtants miſtake themſelves, and forget that we are juſtified and ſaved by the Covenant of Grace, and not by the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or Covenant of our Creation. Chriſt came into the World to procure and tender a new law, and in this regard is he ſaid to be our Law-giver: not that he hath given any other moral rules of, life to us (for we know his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement only is <hi>Love</hi>) than what was contained in the Law before, wherein ſome do but boldly impoſe upon themſelves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43929:15"/>and others: but that he hath given the ſame precepts with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</hi> If God then ſhall not deal with man in his juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here, and at judgment according to that <hi>indulgence,</hi> or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law now in Chriſts hands, that is according to the Covenant of Grace, the main buſineſs of Chriſt coming and redemption were loſt. You ſhall hear a Proteſtant in his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er appealing from the Tribunal of Gods juſtice, to the throne of his grace, and yet in his Sermon be telling the people that it is nothing elſe but the perfect obedience and ſatisfaction of Chriſt imputed to them that ſaves them; which is to bring them back from the <hi>throne of his grace,</hi> to the <hi>bar of his juſtice</hi> to be judged. Such appeals have been received I ſuppoſe from the Fathers, as very ſignificant of truth, and their meaning: but not agreeable to this notion.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, there is a righteouſneſs revealed in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that God went by in his dealing with all the holy men and women who were before Chriſt, and which he goes by in his dealing with us now and all the World, whereby it is that we are juſtified in oppoſition to the <hi>righteouſneſs of works,</hi> the which together with the <hi>grace of the Goſpel</hi> in the true ſenſe and import thereof, is kept out of the <hi>Proteſtant underſtanding</hi> by this noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the rigid imputation of Chriſts righteouneſs in it ſelf, that being alſo but a late and forced notion, and not tending to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs of life, (though they have bin holy men that have received it.) It is on the hearts I find of ſeveral Perſons, and ſorts of Perſons diſagreeing otherwiſe in their way (the providence of the Almighty who is the Authour, being the Conductor of all truth to its proper uſe and end,) to ſhew themſelves againſt it, and to advance this tenent (if I may offer the determination) to the contrary. That the juſtification of a ſinner is not by the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſs made his in it ſelf by faith as an inſtrument: but by the <hi>righteouſneſs of faith,</hi> to wit, by Chriſts righteouſneſs, as the meritorious cauſe, and his faith and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution firſt, and ſincere obedience added after, as the condition of pardon and life through him: or by our ſincere obedience proceeding from faith, which being in it ſelf but imperfect as to the Law, is imputed for righteouſneſs to the ſinner for Chriſts merits ſake, through the grace of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But now the righteouſneſs of God without the law is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43929:15"/>having witneſs of the Law and the Prophets. <hi>Si ergo nunc manifeſtata eſt, etiam tunc erat ſed occulia. If it be now manifeſted, t muſt have bin before lying hid. Aug. de peccato originali cont. Pel &amp; Cel. c.</hi> 25. <hi>Et tunc ergo iſta gratia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatoris erat in populo Dei, ſed tanquam in vellere pluvia. And then was there this grace of the Mediator among Gods people as the rain in the fleece,</hi> that is, though unſeen or not underſtood. <hi>Ib.</hi> I obſerve here that the <hi>righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and the <hi>grace</hi> of the Mediator, is rightly made by this Father to be one. We are ſaid to be juſtified by <hi>grace,</hi> and not by <hi>works:</hi> ſo by the <hi>righteouſneſs which is of God,</hi> and not of <hi>works.</hi> What then is that righteouſneſs of God which is the grace of Chriſt, and by which we are juſtified? By this grace and righteouſneſs, it is certain, that <hi>Auſtine</hi> underſtands inherent grace, which is a quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty infuſed by the Spirit in our hearts, enabling us to good works, and that this way do the Papiſts go after him, according to what alſo is ſaid before. <hi>Iſtam quippe gratiam qua juſtificamur, id eſt, qua Charitas Dei diffunditur in cordibus noſtris— De gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Chriſti, c.</hi> 30. that is, <hi>grace whereby we are juſtified, is no other but the love of God ſhed abroad in our hearts,</hi> or the grace of Charity whereby faith is made perfect, and ſo juſtifies as they and he agree. Now this grace is oppoſed to works, and called the righteouſneſs <hi>which is of God,</hi> and not of <hi>works</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them (which hath been ſaid before likewiſe) becauſe it is that which is given or infuſed of God, and not wrought by our own ſtrength, or procured by our deſerts. <hi>Juſtitia ex lege di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur quae fit propter legis mandatum, juſtitia ex Deo dicitur quae datur per gratiae beneficium. Ib. c.</hi> 12. <hi>That is ſaid to be the righteouſneſs of the law or of works, which is done through the ſtrength of our ſelves only upon the command: that is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God which we are helpt to do by the benefit of grace.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Non dicitur juſtitia noſtra ſed Dei, quia ſic ſit noſtrum ut nobis ex Deo. It is not ſaid our righteouſneſs, but the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God becauſe it is ours ſo as to be firſt given of God.</hi> In the ſame Chapter and Book. The truth is, this Father being poſſeſſed with his own diſpute, as it is incidental to the mind to faſhion all things according to the impreſſions it hath received, does frame ſuch a meaning ſtill in the words of the Apoſtle, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43929:16"/>if <hi>Paul</hi> as well as he, were purpoſely writing againſt <hi>Pelagius.</hi> There are three things in the ſoul ſaid that learned Perſon, <hi>Poſſe, Velle, &amp; Eſſe, Poſſibilitas, Voluntas &amp; Actio,</hi> as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, the <hi>Power,</hi> the <hi>Will,</hi> and the <hi>Deed.</hi> The grace of God he accounted was converſant only about the <hi>Power,</hi> and not the <hi>Will,</hi> or the <hi>Action.</hi> Not that he placed all grace only in the giving the power, for that muſt confound Grace and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indeed quite, ſeeing all have the power: but allowing grace to lye in divine <hi>help</hi> the <hi>power</hi> alone he held was <hi>aided</hi> by God, and the <hi>will</hi> left to its ſelf. This <hi>aid</hi> now in explaining himſelf he confined to Doctrine. God he ſaid does reveal what he would have done in his law, and in the goſpel, and gives us beſides Chriſts example, and then the will of it ſelf (the power alone thus helped) embraces that which is good. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore ſets himſelf to prove, that God does not aſſiſt us only by his word, but by operating on the will, and giving us hearts alſo to do it. And for as much we do nothing of our ſelves but by his help, or by the operation of his ſpirit, it is by grace, ſayes he, that we are juſtified, and not by works. <hi>Quomodo eſt gratia ſi non gratis data? quomodo eſt gratia ſi ex debito redditur? How is it grace if it be not of free gift? How is it grace if it be rendred as debt? De gra. Chr. c.</hi> 23. Again, <hi>Non enim Dei gratia erit ullo modo niſi gratuita fuerit omni mode. It cannot be the grace of God at all, if it be not free altogether, De pec. or. c.</hi> 24. One would think this Father in ſuch ſpeeches as theſe had imbibed the Proteſtant notion of <hi>grace;</hi> but we are miſtaken, for his thoughts ſtill ran upon the Grace of God infuſed in our hearts, that is, the inherent work of the ſpirit which he pleads to be <hi>gratuitous,</hi> becauſe it is not at <hi>firſt</hi> given for our <hi>merits.</hi> The works which we do of our ſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace he accounts merits nothing, but are ſplendid ſinnes: the works which we do from grace or by the ſpirit do juſtifie according to him, and merit eternal ſalvation. <hi>Quod ſi vocatus vocantem ſecutus fuerit, quod eſt in libero arbitrio, merebitur &amp; ſpiritum ſanctum per quem bona poſſit operari: in quo permanens quod niholominus eſt in libero arbitrio, merebitur vitam aeternam quae nulla poſſit labi corrumpi. But if he that is called ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his call, which is in our free will, he ſhall merit the holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43929:16"/>by whoſe help good works may be performed: wherein if he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veres, which is no leſs in his power, he ſhall merit eternal life, which is perfect and never fadeth away. In lib. ex poſ. ad Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</hi> The Proteſtant meeting with this doctrine in the Papiſt are no wayes ſatisfied with ſuch an interpretation. By the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> therefore, as by the <hi>grace</hi> of God, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>works,</hi> they will by all means conceive of a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without us, that is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is not ours by <hi>performance,</hi> but by <hi>faith.</hi> But neither the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants after <hi>Luther,</hi> nor the Papiſt after <hi>Auſtine</hi> have bit the mind of the Apoſtle. The <hi>righteouſneſs of God</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to <hi>works</hi> is really nothing elſe but the meritorious righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, procuring the pardoning Covenant of grace, and our performing the condition: that is, the righteouſneſs of the Covenant of <hi>grace</hi> accepted by God for Chriſts ſake, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the righteouſneſs of the Covenant of <hi>works.</hi> Only we are to know this <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> may be underſtood either with reſpect to <hi>God</hi> as it is all one I ſay with his <hi>grace:</hi> or with reſpect to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> as it is all one with that, upon which this grace is vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed. <hi>Charitas Dei dicta eſt diffundi in cordibus noſtris, non qua nos ipſe diligit, ſed qua nos facit dilectores ſuos: ſicut juſtitia Dei, qua juſti ejus munere efficimur. As it is called the love of God whereby we are made to love him, ſo the righteouſneſs of God whereby we are made righteous through his gift. Aug. de ſpir. &amp; lit. c.</hi> 32. It is true that this righteouſneſs is wrought in us by the ſpirit, and flowes not from our ſelves; it is true al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that as we performe it by his aid, it is our own work: yet is not the one the reaſon why it is called the <hi>righteouſneſs of God,</hi> nor the other any hindrance why it ſhould not be ſo called: for the reaſon lyes altogether in the oppoſition of it meerly to that of <hi>works.</hi> Let a man do all that he can, whether by his own ſtrength, or by Gods aid, he can never come up to the law of works, or to a conformity to the terms of the Covnant of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as it was a repreſentation of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſo that by the deeds thereof he cannot be juſtified: and for as much as it pleaſed God therefore to vouchſafe us a new law, the law of faith, or grace, or the new Covenant ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lower terms, that in the performance hereof, or in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43929:17"/>only hereunto, the man who is a ſinner in reſpect of the law, may be righteous, and ſo God juſt in juſtifying him; this grace and condeſcention of God being meerly from his own good will, is called thus the <hi>righteouſneſs which is of him,</hi> in oppoſition to the other which is of <hi>nature:</hi> and ſo were ours, <hi>or mans righteouſneſs</hi> properly, if he could attain unto the ſame. But when he cannot attain unto that which is ſo by <hi>nature,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he attains, if it be leſs, muſt be a righteouſneſs only through <hi>grace,</hi> which notwithſtanding our ſhortneſs, God mercifully condeſcends to accept, inſtead of that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, through the merits of our Saviour, and in regard of that acceptation <hi>(N. B.)</hi> it is called <hi>his,</hi> or the righteouſneſs <hi>which is of him</hi> (of his own free tender and allowance), when in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of performance it is ours, though we do it by his help. Lo here the true key that opens the mind of the Apoſtle, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the door to that treaſure which depends upon it.</p>
            <p>That which is ſaid I know by our Proteſtants moſt to the quick is this, that <hi>pardon</hi> indeed is an act of meer <hi>grace,</hi> but <hi>juſtification</hi> is an act of <hi>juſtice</hi> according to law, and therefore muſt Chriſts is an act of <hi>juſtice</hi> according to law, and therefore muſt Chriſts righteouſneſs which alone does anſwer the law be brought in to juſtifie the believer. But this is a miſtake, for if juſtification lyes not altogether in pardon [<hi>Even as</hi> David <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the bleſſedneſs of the man unto whom God imputeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs without works, ſaying, bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven</hi>] it is at leaſt one part of it, and the whole is expreſly declared by the Apoſtle to be <hi>by grace, being juſtified freely by his grace.</hi> True indeed it is an act of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> even a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial or forenſical act, that is according to law, but what law? not the <hi>law of works,</hi> but according to the <hi>law of Faith.</hi> It is an act I ſay of that <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of God, and no other which the Apoſtle ſets forth in oppoſition to the <hi>law</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> and makes all one with his <hi>grace.</hi> To reckon it then an act of juſtice according to the Law, intending thereby the law of works, is to correct the Apoſtle, and to tell him we know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how we are juſtified by Chriſt then he. It is the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this righteouſneſs whereof we are now ſpeaking will ſet us all right. It is Chriſts obedience and ſufferings alone no doubt which could make any compenſation to God for our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43929:17"/>ſins, that he might without diminuition to his honour as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, or Governour, recede from his firſt law, but when Chriſt hath by his ſatisfaction procured this that God ſhould now deal with us by a new law, the remedying law, or upon other terms, the thing is manifeſt in itſelf, that the righteouſneſs then which is pleaded and accepted for this ſatisfaction ſake of Chriſt, muſt be this righteouſneſs of the new law, or the righteouſneſs of <hi>faith</hi> and not of <hi>works;</hi> which both denominates the performer righteous, and God juſt in juſtifying him according to it. <hi>For Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſneſs to every one that believeth.</hi> That is, as I conſtrue it, Chriſt by his ſatisfaction hath procured that we ſhould not be judged by the law of works, and conſequently that righteouſneſs, or juſtification, be attained if we do but perform the terms of the Goſpel. <hi>To declare I ſay at this time his righteouſneſs that he might be juſt and a juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him that belives in Jeſus. Who is made unto us of God,</hi> (that is a phraſe I take it ſignifying no more then through whom (one way or other) God would have us obtain all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bleſſings) <hi>wiſdome, righteouſneſs, ſanctification, and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this there are no texts I count (ſuch as the laſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely mentioned) which are preſſed by our Divines for their ſervice before, that are able to carry ſuch a burden. <hi>He hath made him ſin for us</hi> (ſin, as the expiatory ſacrifice under the law is called ſin) <hi>who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him.</hi> That is, he who was the imaculate Lamb was made a ſacrifice for our ſins, that we may become righteous with the righteouſneſs of God, which he accepts through him. Chriſt as a Sacrifie redeems us from the law of ſin, and purchaſes for us a law of grace: according to that law we have a righteouſneſs which is accepted unto life through Chriſt. I pray note it therefore, it is not ſaid that his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs might be made ours, nor that we might be made his righteouſneſs: but that we might be made <hi>the righteouſneſs of God.</hi> And what is the righteouſneſs of God I have ſhewen you juſt now, and what <hi>in him</hi> likewiſe is declared here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with it, in theſe few words. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſimus juſtitia Dei in ipſo. Haec eſt illa juſtitia Dei, non qua ipſe juſtus eſt, ſed qua nos ab eo facti. That we ſhould become the righteouſneſs of God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43929:18"/>in him. This is that righteouſneſs of God, not whereby he is righteous, but whereby we are made ſo of him. Auguſtine</hi> again, in the laſt cited place. It is true then there is a righteouſneſs, of <hi>faith,</hi> and righteouſneſs of <hi>God</hi> (of faith as the root of the whole condition) which are one, and by which in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the <hi>righteouſneſs of works</hi> we are juſtified: but that this righteouſneſs of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Faith,</hi> is only the obedience of Chriſts life and death which he performed for us, is aſſumed as much without reaſon, as any conſent of that Father. To this purpoſe, I take it, is God ſtyled in the Old Teſtament, <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, in his condeſcention to accept us for Chriſts ſake as righteous by a law of grace, when in ſtrict juſtice he might condemn us for ſinners. It is not appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſecond Perſon, but to be underſtood of that Goſpel goodneſs of God whereby he imputeth righteouſneſs to us, when we have none according to the law of our creation, that is imputing the righteouſneſs of faith to us without the works of that Covenant. <hi>All our merits O Lord</hi> (ſayes the Father) <hi>are thy mercy.</hi> This is the true and exellent import of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſignifying moreover that God that found out the means to demonſtrate his juſtice no leſs fully (and his goodneſs more fully) to the World in ſaving us by this new law, through his Sons mediation, then if we had kept our firſt innocency, or underwent his eternal judgment for our tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>Another text which is a fellow with this, I take it in ſenſe and words, is that to the <hi>Romans. As by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners: ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous:</hi> I comment theſe words thus. As through <hi>Adams</hi> ſin we came into the ſtate of the fall, and ſo do all ſin, or are ſinners againſt the law, which none fulfil: ſo by Chriſts obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Father whereby he procured the grace of a new law for us we are brought to ſuch a ſtate, as that many become righteous, and are juſtified by the performance. That all man-kind is involved in <hi>Adams</hi> firſt ſin, our Divines are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed againſt <hi>Pelagius.</hi> The moſt underſtand this to come through the <hi>Covenant</hi> or <hi>Will</hi> of God: there are ſome apt to conceive only that <hi>Adam</hi> being the natural root of mankind, human nature it ſelf ſinned in him, and ſo when we come to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43929:18"/>exiſt, his guilt is derived upon our perſons as <hi>virtually</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minally</hi> in him, no otherwiſe then <hi>Levi</hi> is ſaid to have paid tyths to <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> in the loyns of <hi>Ahraham.</hi> I ſhould incline to this explanation, but that I ſee not then why all the ſins of <hi>Adam</hi> beſides, and of all our Progenitors, ſhould not be <hi>ours</hi> alſo upon the ſame account, as much as that <hi>firſt</hi> tranſgreſſion. Diſtinguiſh we therefore between the <hi>precept,</hi> thou ſhalt not eat of the Tree, under this Covenant: and the <hi>threatning</hi> upon breach of it. The Precept plainly belong'd to our firſt Parents only, and as none of us broke that precept which we had not, ſo can we not be reputed to have that ſin (in it ſelf) which we never committed: nevertheleſs the penalty being by the Will or Covenant of God to extend to their progeny (which falls out ordinarily in mans laws alſo), that ſin of <hi>Adams</hi> which <hi>in it ſelf</hi> could be <hi>his</hi> only, in the <hi>effects</hi> threatned upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion does become <hi>ours</hi> alſo. God does ſo impute that act to us, that we are all, as well as he, deprived of original righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, corrupted in our nature, and ſure to dye: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (I take it) are we to conceive of the imputation both of our ſins to Chriſt, and of his righteouſneſs to us. Our ſins are not laid upon him to make him a ſinner: but to be a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſins. He was not made ſin or accounted a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>quoad reatum culpae,</hi> as if he were guilty of our facts, but he was dealt with as a ſinner, <hi>quoad reatum paenae,</hi> in regard to the obligation unto ſatisfaction, which as a <hi>Sponſor</hi> he was to make in our behalf. The righteouſneſs of Chriſt likewiſe which he performed as <hi>Sponſor</hi> or <hi>Mediator,</hi> cannot be ours either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally or repreſentatively <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> becauſe this righteouſneſs as Mediator is proper to his Perſon, and is not the very ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of any, or all of us in the law it ſelf: but his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as Mediator, even his whole ſubmiſſion to the law of his Mediatorſhip in life and death, is ours <hi>reſpectively</hi> as to what it procured, or to what he intended it ſhould procure, in aſmuch as we are partakers of the benefits that derive from it. Our <hi>ſins</hi> were <hi>Chriſts</hi> in the <hi>cauſation</hi> of his ſufferings: Chriſts <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes</hi> is <hi>ours</hi> in the <hi>effects</hi> of pardon and life eternal.</p>
            <p>A third text, and which carryes our Divines I think more then any, is that to the <hi>Phillipians. I count all things but loſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43929:19"/>that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him not having mine own righteouſneſs which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</hi> In theſe words, our Proteſtants obſerve that the righteouſneſs of God, and of faith, is oppoſed to that righteouſneſs which is our <hi>own,</hi> and therefore it muſt be a righteouſneſs <hi>without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith. But they are miſtaken, for, beſides that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of <hi>faith</hi> and of <hi>God,</hi> is not the ſame with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as hath been before obſerved, they are to know that this righteouſneſs which <hi>Paul</hi> calls his <hi>own</hi> in this Text, is the righteouſneſs of the <hi>Jew,</hi> that is, the <hi>Jews own,</hi> or his own as a <hi>Jew</hi> and a <hi>Phariſee;</hi> not <hi>our own,</hi> or his own as a Chriſtian. This appears from the Verſes before. <hi>If any think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he hath whereof he may truſt in the fleſh, I more, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed the eighth day, an Hebrew of the Hebrews, as touching the law a Phariſee, as touching the righteouſneſs which of the law blameleſs.</hi> This appears farther from another text, which together with this alone is all that hath any ſuch Antitheſis in the Terms <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence they fetch this conjecture. <hi>I bear them record that they have a Zeal for God, but not according to knowledg. For they being ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, and going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God.</hi> It is certain now from theſe places both, that there is a righteouſneſs which was <hi>Pauls own</hi> and the <hi>Jews own</hi> which he excluds from juſtification, and oppoſes to the righteouſneſs of <hi>faith</hi> and of <hi>God:</hi> but this I ſay is not the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> righteouſneſs. The Chriſtians faith and new obedience are his own acts out of doubt by Gods help, and <hi>his</hi> righteouſneſs according to the Goſpel: and you ſhall never read St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaying, <hi>I deſire to be found in Chriſt not having my own repentance, my own</hi> faith, love, and new obedience, which are conditions of being <hi>found in him</hi> that we may be juſtifyed. <hi>Pauls</hi> own righteouſneſs as a <hi>Jew,</hi> or as a <hi>Phariſee</hi> I ſay is one thing, and <hi>Pauls</hi> faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is his righteouſneſs as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is another. And this diſtinction our Saviour himſelf hath firſt offered. <hi>Except your righteouſneſs, exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſes</hi>— The righteouſneſs of works is twofold. The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43929:19"/>of <hi>Mankind,</hi> according to the Covenant of Nature: and the righteouſneſs of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> while they reckoned to be juſtified by the external obſervation only of the rites of <hi>Moſes.</hi> The one of theſe <hi>exceeds</hi> the righteouſneſs of faith, and we are not juſtified by it, becauſe no man can attain to it: the other <hi>falls ſhort</hi> of the righteouſneſs of faith, or of a true Chriſtian, according to theſe words of our Lord, and for that reaſon, as for ſeveral others, the eſtabliſhment of it was dangerous to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>A laſt text they have, <hi>what the law could not do in that it was weak through the fleſh, God ſending his own Son in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, and for ſin condemned ſin in the fleſh: that the righteouſneſs of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh but after the Spirit.</hi> It is urged here by a Perfectiſt, that if the Proteſtant doctrine were true, it ſhould be ſaid that the righteouſneſs of the law ſhould be fulfilled in Chriſt, and not in us. But theſe words I apprehend may be a phraſe of the Apoſtles, as the words <hi>attaining unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> otherwhere: and ſo it will be all one as if he had ſaid, <hi>that we might be juſtified, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> Nevertheleſs, there is this here muſt be known and noted, that when a Chriſtian obeys God according to the Goſpel, that obedience of his proceeding from faith, though imperfect, is accepted of God inſtead of the laws perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or ſtands him in the ſtead as if the whole law were fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which is the ground of ſuch expreſſions. From whence in the way we may have light for the underſtanding the Apoſtle, when he tells us <hi>the law is eſtabliſhed by faith,</hi> or uſes the like words. The law is eſtabliſhed only by the fulfilling of it: and faith as it works by love fulfils the law. But how? why in the ſenſe <hi>(N. B.)</hi> as is now told you. Faith produces obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which is imperfect, yet anſwering the terms of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it is, through that grace and condeſcention from God which Chriſt hath purchaſed for us in the work of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, imputed to us for righteouaneſs, that is, accepted and rewarded ſo, as it is made to ſtand us in the ſame ſtead as the full performance of the law would have done, which is to juſtifie us, and bring us life eternal.</p>
            <p>When God made man he gave him a law ſuitable to his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43929:20"/>That law being founded in the image of God, wherein he was created, is moſt holy, equal, and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. God as Rector muſt deal with the World accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this law, ſo that man tranſgreſſing, he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to proceed againſt him by it, unleſs there be ſome means found out that he may be no loſer in his juſtice if he do not. There is nothing can be offered to God but his juſtice and holineſs muſt be loſers, if it be of conſideration leſs va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable then that which the law it ſelf required, which is the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all mankind, or their everlaſting ſuffering for its tranſgreſſion. No Man or Creature but Chriſt alone could offer any ſuch ſatisfaction as this for us. And this he offered in the obedience or righteouſneſs of his whole life and death, as the price, ſacrifice, ranſome, propitiation for our ſins: which through the dignity of the Perſon that offered it, being the Son of God as well as man, was of value which is infinite. That which exceeds a thing or is more in value then it, cannot be the very thing it ſelf which in value it exceeds. The righteouſneſs then of Chriſt is really imputed to man, tendred in his behalf, and made ours in regard of this effect (or <hi>in the end</hi> to which it was intended I will ſay, when it cannot be ours <hi>in it ſelf</hi>), to wit, that God being ſatisfied or made no loſer in his juſtice hereby, does deal with us otherwiſe then by that law unto which at firſt we were created. If he deals not with us then accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, it muſt be by ſome other, which hereby alſo is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed; and that is according to his <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Goſpel. This grace or righteouſneſs lyes in his acceptance of faith and repentance inſtead of perfect obedience for this righteouſneſs ſake of Chriſt thus imputed, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then thus. When our Divines now ſay that there are no works of ours can ſtand before God in his diſtrict judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they ſhould be <hi>cauſa propter quam, the cauſe for which,</hi> (that is for the merit ſake, or worthineſs whereof) he ſhould juſtifie any perſon, they ſay well; and there meaning is, that our works coming not up to the <hi>original law,</hi> God cannot for the performance of them, abſolve us as no ſinners: but yet ſeeing they are ſuch as anſwer the terms of the Goſpel, he does for Chriſts ſake, or his merits ſake, both pardon their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and impute them to us for righteouſneſs, in the accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43929:20"/>them to life, or rewarding them with everlaſting ſalvation. In ſhort Chriſts righteouſneſs is imputed to us, but not for righteouſneſs. It is <hi>for the righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> but not formally though efficiently <hi>by the righteouſneſs</hi> of another, we are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It is not Chriſt, but our ſelves, that perform the new Covenant, and by the <hi>new Covenant</hi> is it, or by <hi>grace,</hi> that we are righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Gods ſight. It is not conſequently Chriſts ſufferings or obedience only, but our faith, obedience, ſincerity alſo, that is rewarded with ſalvation: yet is it not for the merit of this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of ours, but for his merits, or the merits of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. Behold! this is the critrical hindge upon which the whole controverſie does turn. We will ſtand for the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſs <hi>(N. B.)</hi> ſo far as ever we can with hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtification by the Covenant of grace: but when ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have ſtood for it ſo, as renders our juſtification to be by the <hi>law,</hi> or the Covenant of works, and not by <hi>grace,</hi> they have departed from the Apoſtle. And thus the diſpute in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot will I think end in this, that Chriſts righteouſneſs is the <hi>meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious,</hi> indeed the <hi>only meritorious,</hi> or meritoriouſly <hi>procuring effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,</hi> but muſt not be made the <hi>formal</hi> cauſe of mans juſtification.</p>
            <p>And yet do I ſee there is need ſtill of ſome more words, ſeeing here the heart of all lyes. A righteouſneſs we muſt have if we be juſtified, and what is that righteouſneſs? There is a <hi>legal</hi> righteouſneſs: and <hi>Evangelical.</hi> Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs our Divines account our Legal righteouſneſs which muſt anſwer the law for us: and our faith and repentance muſt be produced to anſwer the Goſpel. The latter of theſe I take to be plain: the former muſt be warily underſtood. There is the <hi>Precept,</hi> and the <hi>Retribution</hi> of the law. We muſt take heed that we conceive not Chriſt to be our legal righteouſneſs in regard to the <hi>Preceptive</hi> part of the law (in the more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſenſe) as if we were reputed by God to have fulfilled the ſame, or ſatisfied it in him as repreſenting our Perſons, which is the errour before confuted, and eſpecially by the reaſon laſt mentioned, becauſe this makes our juſtification to be by the law of <hi>works,</hi> (and not of <hi>grace</hi>) which ſubverts the Goſpel: but there is a righteouſneſs in regard to the <hi>retributive</hi> part of the law of works, conſiſting in our diſcharge from its curſe and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43929:21"/>penalty, which is a <hi>righteouſneſs of pardon,</hi> and if any will call this our <hi>legal</hi> righteouſneſs (which is yet conferred by the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi>) and account we have it in Chriſt, underſtanding nothing elſe by it, but that his righteouſneſs is the meritorious cauſe of it, I know not any will oppoſe him. It is true, that <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> without explication is a contradiction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we allow of a <hi>righteouſneſs of pardon,</hi> there is a <hi>ſtrict</hi> and a <hi>large</hi> ſenſe to be acknowledged of <hi>terms</hi> uſe in Scripture. Bleſſed is the man <hi>unto whom God imputeth righteouſneſs without works.</hi> The imputation of righteouſneſs to a perſon is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him righteous; and for a man to be accounted righteous <hi>without works,</hi> that is without righteouſneſs, is explained in the next verſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to be <hi>pardoned.</hi> By <hi>works,</hi> he underſtands works of the <hi>law</hi> out of doubt, for without faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (or <hi>Goſpel</hi> works) God imputes righteouſneſs to none. Now how a man may be righteous according to the <hi>law of grace,</hi> and yet need pardon in reference to the <hi>law of works,</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is plain: but to make a man <hi>righteous</hi> (through this pardon) in regard to the <hi>retribution,</hi> and <hi>guilty</hi> in regard to the <hi>precept</hi> of the ſame law, is to ſpeak I account <hi>Scripturali licentia,</hi> by leave of the Scripture. To be acquitted from the condemnation of a law by being pronounced innocent, or to be adjudged to the reward by being declared to have fulfilled it, is in the ſtrict ſenſe to be juſtified: To be acquitted from the condemnation, and be pronounced guilty, is to be <hi>delivered</hi> from the law, and not to be <hi>juſtified,</hi> but in a large fence of juſtification. Juſtification <hi>from</hi> a law, and not <hi>by</hi> it, is a catechreſtical ſpeech, and I do queſtion whether we ſhould not (uſing a ſtrict ſpeaking) place the diſcharge of the ſinner from condemnation, upon the ſcore of Chriſts <hi>redemption,</hi> rather then on the work of our <hi>juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> That <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World to himſelf not imputing their treſpaſſes</hi> does import an univerſal conditional remiſſion beſtowed upon all, ſo far as a delivery of the whole World over from the <hi>law of works</hi> to be judged by the <hi>law of grace;</hi> and when we are at that bar, there is no inqueſt like to be made about Chriſts work whether he hath done his part; but whether we have done ours, that is performed our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if we be found to have bin upright to God in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43929:21"/>main bent of our hearts and lives, notwithſtanding our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold failings, he accepts of us for Chriſts ſake, and declares us righteous according to this law: and ſo adjudges us to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or promiſe, which is to have Chriſt and his benefits, whereof one is the application of his redemption, and therein our diſcharge from the Laws condemnation. And thus methinks the Apoſtle ſpeaks with more acurateneſs, where juſtification and redemption are <hi>de induſtria</hi> diſtinguiſhed, and the one made the means or foundation to the other. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace through the redemption which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the delivery of the World in general from the law, and ſo from its penalty on terms appointed by the Redeemer: Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is the pronouncing of particular perſons accepted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe terms, and ſo to have a right to the purchaſed poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In fine, there is but our own ſincerity, and a right to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity and life, is all the righteouſneſs that we have, or that can go (in it ſelf) to the juſtification of a ſinner. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of all is, we are not to conceive a ſinner to be brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two barrs that he ſhould have need of a righteouſneſs of perfect obedience in Chriſt to plead againſt the law, for Chriſt hath redeemed us from coming before this barre, by the ranſome of his blood paid for all the World: but being to ſtand only at one bar, it is but one righteouſneſs is ſought as the condition upon which the ſentence muſt paſs, and as for that Righteouſneſs we have through Chriſt beſides, which is in regard only to the <hi>retribution,</hi> not the <hi>work</hi> of the law, that is to ſay Pardon, it comes to us by way of ſentence, or as a part of the reward given upon the condition performed, but is not part of the condition, or the whole condition it ſelf pleaded for our juſtification. Only the redemption of Chriſt, I count is to be firſt ſuppoſed, with the whole righteouſneſs of his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as the foundation, through the merits whereof, this new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is purchaſed, and ſo the reward given, for his ſake, upon that condition. And if it be for Chriſts ſake, for his merits, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, mediation, redemption ſake, we ſee alſo how this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his, even his Mediatory righteouſneſs which cannot be ours poſſibly <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> is yet imputed to us and made ours in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43929:22"/>the <hi>effects,</hi> or in the end to which it was performed, for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Believers.</p>
            <p>I will conclude all with the agreement of the two Apoſtles, which hath been already, but lightly, before touched.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> then contends, that a man is not juſtified by the works of the law. By the works of the law, he means works as would juſtify him according to law if he had them, and ſayes no man is juſtified hereby, becauſe no man hath them, as he proves at large in the firſt and ſecond Chapters to the <hi>Romans,</hi> as the very buſineſs and ſcope of both, to any that will conſider of the matter, and ſo pleads a neceſſity of their <hi>believing that they may be juſtified.</hi> But when St. <hi>James</hi> ſayes a man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by works, he means not works that anſwer the law, or ſuch as of themſelves would juſtifie the doer, which no man hath, neither <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, much leſs <hi>Rahab</hi> whom he alſo men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſuch works as ſuppoſe grace to their acceptance through faith in the Redeemer, for the reconciling the Perſon, and covering his imperfections. And thus the two holy Penmen diſagree not: but while the one faith, <hi>I conclude a man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith without the works of the law,</hi> and the other, <hi>You ſee then how that by works a man is juſtified, and not by faith only,</hi> the ſenſe of both is, that though a man hath not the works of the law (the works the law <hi>qua faedus</hi> requires of him) which would juſtifie the doer if he did them (as for certain he does not, it being impoſſible for any to have theſe, ſo that if he be juſtifyed at all, he muſt be juſtified without them): yet is he juſtified by faith, provided that faith be accompanied with (or is the <hi>initium</hi> and <hi>fundamentum</hi> of) good works of another ſize; to wit, that will not make the reward to be of <hi>debt,</hi> but of <hi>grace,</hi> or that are unperfect and not able to juſtify him by law, yet are required in ſincerity of life, together with his faith in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer (ſuppoſing him revealed, or elſe in the mercifulneſs of Gods nature) unto final juſtification, and ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And now Reader if thou art offended at this paper, I cannot help thy prejudice, but I deſire thee to hear reaſon. If thou art ſenſible of that deadly advantage which is given to the Papiſts,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43929:22"/>by our ill treating this point, by the doctrine I mean more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, of Chriſts righteouſneſs <hi>imputed</hi> in the unſound ſenſe, eſpecially when thoſe that expound it worſe, do ordinarily lay moſt ſtreſs upon it: If thou art ſenſible yet neerer home, what a ſtumbling block hereby hath been laid in the way of a late nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Sect among us (whom to name methinks is ſome rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them), that really having our Miniſters here by the lock (that is the place where their only ſtrength they have againſt us does lye), do reject the whole Tribe, as Falſe Teachers that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour men in their ſins, and make Chriſt ſerve only to be a cover for them, as they bitterly traduce us, with great indignation, and in very earneſt on this account (which I muſt confeſs hath affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me ſo much in reading their books, as to ſet me to write, and gives me yet a good conſcience in what I do, though thou perhaps art angry with me for it): If laſtly thou art ſenſible of the evil and danger of <hi>Libertiniſme</hi> or <hi>Antinomianiſme,</hi> which hath been lately ſo rife, though now allayed in this Land, what roots yet it hath alive in this notion miſ-underſtood, thou wilt be adviſed with me, and others perhaps that ſee more then I, that it is time, that it is fit, this Sluce be ſtopt. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are my Friends, and the <hi>Independents</hi> my Friends, and Others my Friends, but Truth is greateſt, and muſt overcome.</p>
            <closer>Deo Gloria mihi condonatio.
<signed>JOHN HUMFREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 9. <hi>l. 35.</hi> for juſtified them, <hi>r.</hi> juſtified by them. p. <hi>10. l. 28.</hi> for that, <hi>r.</hi> ſeeing that <hi>(N.B.)</hi> p. <hi>19. l. 14.</hi> for perceptive, <hi>r.</hi> preceptive.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere is a Book came out this Terme, entituled, <hi>Two points of Moment Diſcuſſed,</hi> by the ſame Authour: ſold by Mr. <hi>Million</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
